Guide to the "The Youngest Parents: Teenage Pregnancy as it Shapes Lives" Exhibit Photographs, 1987-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
The Youngest Parents: Teenage Pregnancy as it Shapes Lives Exhibit photographs 1987-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies.
3.0 Linear Feet 24 Items
John Moses, a professor of pediatrics at Duke University, spent eleven years documenting teenage parents in North Carolina counties, including Durham and Orange. Jocelyn Lee is a professor at the Maine College of Art and worked for six years in parts of Texas, Maine, Massachusetts, New York, and Nova Scotia, living and working with young mothers.
Collection of 24 gelatin silver prints from an exhibit, The Youngest Parents: Teenage Pregnancy as it Shapes Lives, displayed at Duke University's Center for Documentary Studies in 1998.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Youngest Parents: Teenage Pregnancy as it Shapes Lives Exhibit Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Biographical and Historical Note
John Moses, photography instructor at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University and a practicing pediatrician, spent eleven years documenting teenage parents in North Carolina counties. Jocelyn Lee, a photography professor at Princeton University, spent six years in parts of Texas, Maine, Massachusetts, New York, and Nova Scotia, living and working with young mothers. Friendships of support and caring developed between the photographers and the teens, and the trust resulting from these relationships deepened the character and meaning of their work. The Youngest Parents exhibition of twenty-five black-and-white photographs taken from 1986 to the present day included follow-up photographs of the young parents, now adults, and their children, now teens and young adults themselves. The exhibit also included text panels with young mothers’ candid reflections.
This exhibit was displayed by the Center for Documentary Studies from May 28 through September 19, 1998.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 24 black-and-white gelatin silver prints, dating from 1987-1996, and sized at either 11" x 14" or 16" x 20". Most of the photographs were taken by Jocelyn Lee in Maine or Texas. A small amount of photographs were taken by John Moses in North Carolina. No additional information or text accompanies the photographs.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Moses, John
Lee, Jocelyn
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
Teenage parents -- Pictorial works
Teenage parents -- Texas -- Manners and customs
Teenage parents -- Maine -- Manners and customs
Teenage parents -- North Carolina -- Manners and customs
North Carolina -- Teenagers -- Pictorial works
Texas -- Teenagers -- Pictorial works
Maine -- Teenagers -- Pictorial works
Parenting -- Pictorial works
Documentary photography
Gelatin silver prints
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- The Youngest Parents: Teenage Pregnancy as it Shapes Lives, 1987-1996, (2 boxes)
  Prints have been arranged by size within two boxes. Box 1 contains prints that are 11" x 14" or smaller. Box 2 contains prints that are 16" x 20" or smaller.
  - Jocelyn Lee: Austin, Texas, 1993. (Box 1)
    Corresponding Page: 144-145. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Austin, Texas, 1993.
    Corresponding Page: 146. Measurements: 11" x 14".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Austin, Texas, 1993.
    Corresponding Page: 152. Measurements: 15 7/8" x 19 7/8"
  - Jocelyn Lee: Austin, Texas, 1994.
    Corresponding Page: 153. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: East Livermore Falls, Maine, 1995
    Corresponding Page: 155. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: 157. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1995.
    Corresponding Page: 160. Measurements: 11" x 14".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: 161. Measurements: 10 7/8" x 14".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: 162. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: 166. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Leander, Texas, 1994.
    Corresponding Page: 167. Measurements: 11" x 14".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: Image is not in publication; same woman as seen on Page 171. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: East Livermore Falls, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: 172. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Leander, Texas, 1995.
    Corresponding Page: 173. Measurements: 11" x 14".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996.
    Corresponding Page: 175. Measurements: 11" x 14".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Austin, Texas, 1993.
    Corresponding Page: 179. Measurements: 13 7/8" x 10 7/8".
  - John Moses: Orange County, North Carolina, 1994
    Corresponding Page: 190. Measurements: 10 7/8" x 13 7/8".
  - John Moses: Granville County, North Carolina, 1987
    Corresponding Page: 198. Measurements: 10 7/8" x 13 7/8".
  - John Moses: Orange County, North Carolina, 1994
    Corresponding Page: 218. Measurements: 10 7/8" x 13 7/8".
  - John Moses: Vance County, North Carolina, 1989
    Corresponding Page: 222-223. Measurements: 10 7/8" x 13 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1996 (Box 2)
    Corresponding Page: 159. Measurements: 16 x 20".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Leander, Texas, 1992
    Corresponding Page: 163. Measurements: 15 7/8" x 19 7/8".
  - Jocelyn Lee: Portland, Maine, 1995
    Corresponding Page: 180. Measurements: 15 7/8" x 19 7/8".
  - John Moses: Orange County, North Carolina, 1994
    Corresponding Page: 196. Measurements: 16" x 20".